[Uhtred] I was born
an Aelderman of England.
Uhtred, son of Uhtred
of Bebbanburg,
welcome to the Christian world.
[Uhtred] True heir to the
Northumbrian lands of Bebbanburg.
You have your stone,
the amber?
Yes, Father.
Our ancestors took this land and
you will die for it, if needed.
I was 12-years-old
when I first went to war.
[man] Kill them all!
I saw my father killed.
My Uncle took my lands
and pledged his allegiance
to the Danes.
My advice to you
is never to cross Ubba
and never, never fight him.
[Uhtred]
Stolen by the invaders,
along with
the Saxon girl, Brida.
I became first a slave,
and then a son to Earl Ragnar.
That was my family. My life.
Young Ragnar, my brother,
and Brida, my lover.
Fate had made me a Dane.
And then fate brought betrayal.
[yelling]
I will not stand by and have
everything that's mine taken from me.
Bebbanburg's is mine!
Destiny is all.
Horses!
Head for the woods.
[yelling indistinct]
Go right, there's a gully
over that ridge.
Hoof-marks.
There must be hoof-marks.
There must be hoof-marks
somewhere!
Fetch more men.
I want him found!
We'll go as far as Mercia
if need be,
but I want him found
and I want him dead.
He looked like my father.
And now he knows you are alive,
he'll keep looking for you.
Let him. I'm going to kill him
and take back what's mine.
He has an army.
He is the choice of the Danes!
All you have is me!
No, we have Ubba.
We go to him with our story.
With his army, we avenge Ragnar's
death and we take back Bebbanburg.
It's that simple?
Yes.
Yes...
[Uhtred] Brida...
Brida... sing me a song.
I won't,
and I'm not your skald.
True, and what's more,
you'd frighten the birds.
What?
There is a taste in the air.
Death.
[birds chirping]
[arrow hisses]
[panting]
[grunts]
Who did this?
Who sacked the village?
[man] I cannot move.
Your back is broken.
[groans in pain]
Who did it?
You know who did this.
Danes did this.
Why?
I don't believe you,
why should the Danes attack
a village that feeds them?
Revenge.
But since when have
Danes needed an excuse to kill?
[Brida]
Revenge, revenge for what?
Huh?
Revenge for what,
and I'll end it.
An uprising north of here.
A Saxon slave, he killed
his master at a wedding party.
[man gasping]
What was the name of the slave?
Huh?
You speak English well
for a Dane.
His name!
[groans]
Uhtred.
End it.
End...
[groans in pain]
-Say it...
-Say what?
What you are thinking.
I'm thinking
that you have a turd
where there's
supposed to be a mind?
[laughing]
Thank you.
We should never
have gone to Bebbanburg.
We should have let them
believe that you were dead!
No, you're wrong.
I want them to know I am alive.
I need them to know I am alive
because they hold what's mine.
I feel better for it.
Yeah, so does a dog
pissing on a tree.
You wish me to bark?
What we needed to do was to ride
south to the Chieftain Ubba,
and tell the story
of Ragnar's death.
We'll do it now.
Now there is a second story,
about some slave
who killed his master.
Ubba knows that Ragnar
was my father.
He knows nothing!
I doubt he'll even remember you!
He will believe the story
that he hears first!
And he will kill you.
If you could write,
then you could write to him.
If he could read.
You've left us no choice.
We must find Ubba
and hope he believes you.
[indistinct chatter]
[bell tolling]
Thank you.
[man] Father Beocca.
Father.
Segwall.
I'll see you in the King's Hall.
My Lord?
My Lord Alfred,
it is I, Father Beocca.
My Lord,
the king has called council.
[Alfred]
Do not look at me Father.
I am a sinner
I'm a grievous sinner.
We are all sinners, my Lord.
And I am married!
I should never have married.
He sends temptation to test us.
And when we fail he sends the Danes
to punish us for that failure.
[Alfred] I should never have married,
I should have joined the church
I should of gone to a monastery.
And God would have found
a great servant in you,
but I feel he has other plans.
If your brother were to die, it would
be to you, the people would turn.
Oh, pray God he does not die.
What kind of king would I be?
You'll be God's king,
my Lord.
You have been blessed and chosen
by the Holy Father in Rome,
you would be God's king.
I have seen the girl who
torments you. She is...
-She must be banished.
-No, I believe the opposite.
She should be
brought into your service.
-No, no I could not.
-You will resist her.
You will let Him
see your strength.
You will thank Him
for tempting you
and then praise Him
for resisting the temptation.
Notwithstanding...
I have news
you may wish to take to council.
What news?
Of an English uprising,
Lord, in the north.
It was defeated.
But the nobleman responsible was
Uhtred of Bebbanburg, I know him.
He was taken by the Danes
as a child, a God-fearing child.
Clearly his heart
remains English.
-He lives?
-I believe so.
He is a warrior, Lord.
They say he killed his
Danish master and 40 men.
He knows their ways,
he speaks their language.
He would be useful,
would he not?
You could mention him
in council?
Why would
he kill his master?
For blood?
For money? For pleasure?
-For England, Lord.
-Yes, but how do we know?
He may well be just one more
Pagan with a busy sword.
Ah, but I know him Lord.
No, Father Beocca,
you knew him, once.
You knew him as a child.
I could send word out
into the country, God willing.
Father, he's a ghost,
he's a Pagan rumor.
Should he become flesh and blood,
then he may merit a mention.
However, my faith,
I reserve for God alone.
Now about this girl?
You may be right about her.
Bring her into my personal
service... and pray for me.
As always, my Lord.
[indistinct chatter]
Alfred.
King Edmund of East Anglia writes
a plea to Wessex, for an army.
An attack by the Danish Chieftain,
Earl Ubba, is inevitable.
This was two days ago.
A long march to fight the Danes
at a place of their choosing
is not a strategy
worth considering.
-To say the least, my Lord.
-I am of a mind to decline.
-And rightly.
-Ubba...
...he is the Dane
whom King Edmund
-has fed and watered in the past?
-He is.
Perhaps in the hope that he
would simply pass through
East Anglia on his way
to invading Wessex.
It is my opinion that Edmond
deserves nothing but silence.
Too harsh, young Odda.
I believe it was Edmund's hope
to convert the Danes
from Pagan to Christian,
beginning with charity.
For that
he deserves praise, surely.
You are true, my Lord,
if indeed that was his hope.
Edmund is a Godly man, we have no reason
to mistake his actions for cowardice.
[Aethelred] Regardless of Edmund's
intentions barring a miracle,
East Anglia will soon
fall to the Danes.
And he shall have all our prayers
for such a miracle, my Lord.
He will need them.
He will not, however,
have one man of Wessex,
-on that we are agreed?
-Yes, Lord.
[all agreeing]
Then we must therefore recognize
that we now stand alone.
The last kingdom of England.
It will soon be the men of Wessex staring
across a field at the Pagan Army.
We must be ready. We must
pray and we must prepare.
Odda, I require Mercia, Lundene and
East Anglia to be watched carefully.
Forward knowledge is everything.
-It is done, my Lord.
-And, scribe,
I require the forges
of every town and village
to be burning, night and day.
We shall need all the iron
those fires can proffer.
Yes, my Lord.
Most of all I require men.
Strong, fighting men
who are prepared to die
because that in the end,
is what it will
take to save us...
...the blood of men.
Ravn used to say,
"Never fight Ubba."
Looks like East Anglia's
just made that mistake.
We should stay away for now.
Build our own fire.
Ubba's unpredictable,
he takes his orders
from the Gods.
[Uhtred] I know,
he only listens to a sorcerer.
And he's half mad.
How will you approach him?
As a man.
It has to be done.
Yes, it has to be done.
But we need to guard your life.
-How?
-I don't know.
We should hump, tonight.
We should, it's written.
That we should hump?
[chuckles] Our destiny is to hump...
tonight.
[chuckles]
I'm enjoying the thought of it.
That's all
you'll enjoy tonight.
[chuckles]
[moaning]
-Stop, stop, stop!
-What? What is it?
I... I think I have it.
We take a hostage, a shield
a guarantee for your life.
Who?
I don't know...
someone he can't do without.
Storri. His sorcerer.
[screaming]
[man]
Who is the woman?
Why is she not on her back?
Not that it's your concern,
but she's for Storri,
a Saxon whore from Ubba.
I've seen you before.
I served Earl Ragnar,
and now I serve Ubba.
[woman screaming]
You'll see me again,
I'm sure, boy.
[chuckles]
I'm told Storri
is at the church.
He's up at the Monastery,
looking after King Edmond
and killing his priests.
[coughing]
[man groans]
Hello?
Leave me or it will be
the death of you!
The church is mine,
by the order of Ubba.
Master Storri,
I have a gift for you.
-Really?
-She is from Earl Ubba.
A woman?
Why would Ubba send me a woman?
-I have no need of a woman.
-She is a sorceress.
He wishes her dead
but is afraid of a curse.
Saggy tits, stinking breath,
but you will be rewarded.
Her head's weight in silver.
A sorceress?
She has the face of a she-wolf.
Does she bite?
-Yes, she bites.
-Leave her with me.
I will do as Ubba asks,
and she will die... slowly.
[grunts]
You belong to me now, old man.
And you will die slowly
unless you do as I say.
On your feet,
we're going for a walk,
and you will
keep your mouth shut!
This is so foolish,
Ubba will come look for me,
and he will be here soon.
I said be quiet.
Then I'll wait for him here.
I'll wait for Ubba here.
That means
it's just you and me.
[horse whinnies]
[man] Where is Storri,
he's supposed to be here?
Edmund?
Edmund...
Ed...
[laughing]
Can we have some ale?
Miserable King Edmund
of East Anglia,
you have had the night
to consider my offer.
How do you answer?
[chuckles]
Are you dead
or breathing still?
With luck, he's dead. We allow far
too many of them to live as it is.
-You allow nothing!
-He lives.
It's God who decides who lives.
I would say your God
has left you hanging, sir.
If he has done so,
it's because it is his will.
Take him down,
and do not to let him fall,
and ale,
and for the Earl Guthrum.
I don't understand,
we do that all time.
We allow half of them to live.
I say we kill them all,
all but the young women.
And who should work the fields?
The old women,
the pregnant women.
Put him there,
and give the man some ale.
Earl Ubba!
If I may speak freely.
-I know you.
-I am Uhtred Ragnarson.
I am here with the truth
of how my father died.
Yes, you are Ragnar's slave,
and you killed him.
I don't know what stories
you've heard but Earl Ragnar
was killed by his own, by Danes.
His former ship's master, Kjartan
and his half-blind son, Sven,
they led the attack on a
sleeping wedding party.
Can't you see that we are
entertaining a king?
Lord Ubba, I am telling you that
Earl Ragnar was killed by Danes!
You will be quiet boy!
And you will wait!
-Kill him.
-Not another word!
Bar the doors,
he does not leave.
Guthrum is right we are
entertaining a king,
so no more interruptions.
I just have to know,
who is that? Mmm!
-His eyes are watching me.
-And me.
Who's... Who's what? Who?
The half-naked image there...
Who is it?
[sighs]
That is the Saint Sebastian.
A former Roman soldier
who found God.
[Guthrum]
Found him where?
He... he found him in his heart!
Not...
Do you wish me
to tell you his story?
I have time.
The Emperor of Rome, on discovering
that Sebastian had found God,
ordered him to renounce
his faith, he refused.
So then the Emperor ordered that he'd
be filled full of arrows and yet...
...he lived.
-He lived?
-Yes, he did.
-Is this true?
-Of course, it's true.
God saved Saint Sebastian and God
should be praised for that mercy.
For how long did he live?
Well, sadly he...
He then ordered that
he be clubbed to death.
So he died.
He went to heaven,
so he lived.
I have heard
mention of this heaven.
What is this heaven?
Heaven is Valhalla, Lord.
To the Christians,
but without
the fighting, feasting
and humping.
Heaven is Heaven,
it is not heathen!
But to answer
your very first question,
I... I have considered
your offer and yes,
I will continue to rule
East Anglia as you suggest.
I will suffer your presence.
I will provide you with horses,
food, coin and hostages,
I will do all that you demand.
But... only if you,
Lord Ubba, and all
of your men... submit to God.
That is my demand.
You must be baptized.
You must stand
in a barrel of water,
and they pour
more water over you.
They want to wash me?
No...
Your scent upsets them, Ubba.
No, to cleanse you
of your sin's,
there's only one God
and I demand that you serve him.
-Kill him now.
-Why must I serve him?
Because God is great!
All powerful! All magnificent!
Have him stop
his yapping and prove it!
Ah, agreed.
Prove to me your god is great.
-Prove it.
-Prove, prove... look here.
-God spared Saint Sebastian.
-But the man still died.
Because it was God's will!
So would your god
protect you from my arrows?
If he was all powerful,
he would.
Yes, if it was God's will,
he would, yes.
[Ubba]
So let us try.
We shall shoot arrows at you
and if you survive...
[chuckle]
...we will all be washed.
Including Guthrum here.
Why not?
Very well.
I will continue to be king,
but we will dispense
with the need for baptisms.
The, uh... the washing.
I withdraw my request.
But you claim
your God is all powerful.
I want it proven.
Strip him.
Archers.
[Guthrum]
Wait!
Tell me, truthfully,
are you afraid?
God is great!
We will see.
Shoot... Shoot!
Ah...
They are my men and only
I tell them when to shoot.
Shoot.
[groaning]
[panting]
Do you now wished to be clubbed,
or will the arrows be sufficient?
You have come a long way, boy, to tell me it
was Danes, and not you, who killed Ragnar.
It was Kjartan and Sven,
Lord, and others.
It's the truth.
Why else would I be here?
-To spy, to lie.
-No, Lord.
[laughing]
-Perhaps to kill me?
-No, Lord.
Have you been washed?
Odin is my God.
But you have been washed?
Yes, Lord.
How did it feel... the washing?
Cold, Lord.
The water was cold.
Nothing else?
I was a child, Lord.
Now I am a Dane.
Yeah, a Dane.
So now let us see if Odin will
protect you from the arrows.
I like this game. Strip him.
-Keep away from me!
-[grunting]
-Not another step!
-Archers at the ready!
-I have a hostage!
-What?
-I have Storri!
-Stop!
If I die, he dies.
If I die, your sorcerer dies
and you're without his guidance.
He lies, I can smell it.
I have proof... his runes.
Storri will be
returned to you safely.
Take his head
from his shoulders!
Guthrum, be quiet!
Have them open the doors.
I will release Storri
when I am clear of this place.
-You go nowhere! Then he dies!
-Your sorcerer dies!
Have them open the doors...
[doors open]
One day I will kill you.
Storri will tell you otherwise.
And I am telling you the truth
about Ragnar.
This is what happens when we
allow too many of them to live.
[shouting]
Excellent, firewood.
You're alive.
That's good.
Did he hear you?
-He did not. Not a word.
-What did he say?
-That he'll kill me.
-Nothing else?
Where's Storri?
What did he say?
-He's naked!
-It was necessary.
He has a branch
up his arse.
Which is why he is naked.
Uhtred...
[groans]
Uhtred, he must have
said something.
He believes the lie.
He believes that
I killed Ragnar.
[horse whinnies]
[grunting]
There's nothing more to do.
[sighs]
We should put distance
between us and this place.
And go where?
Anywhere that's not here.
I say we go to young Ragnar.
-He's in Ireland.
-Then we go to Ireland.
How? In what? We sail in what?
And with whom? Danes?
Then we wait for him to return!
What if he doesn't return,
what then?
Accept it, we're lost.
We're alive
and breathing for a reason.
Brida, we are no longer Danes!
How much for your work?
For a long sword?
You tell me what you need,
and I'll tell you a price.
A warrior sword
to last a lifetime.
And what are you?
Saxon or Dane?
Northumbria.
It will take some time
to make her right...
...which means
she'll be expensive.
If she's right,
I'll pay in silver. How much?
Ten pieces. Half now.
[chuckles]
Six. No more.
Eight and I'll
make her my finest.
Eight, and if she is not your
finest, you will be her first.
[grunts]
I want this stone
set into the handle?
That can be done.
Don't sell it nor lose it.
Ale, my Lord?
You stand too close, girl.
Just a little to take away
the taste of the gruel.
You stand too close.
It is broth, not gruel.
-Is it?
-Well, I think it is.
You should be thanking God
for its goodness
and the banishment
of those awful cramps.
I am happy to eat as you eat.
You are saintly, my dear.
Father Beocca, join us for
breakfast, I dare you.
Alas, my Lord,
I've already eaten.
You're fortunate.
Bad news, Lord.
Your nephew. Aethelwold.
Isn't it always?
He's drunk, he's sleeping
in the palace garden.
Should I take him to the king?
It's the second time this week.
May God strike him down...
painfully.
[snoring]
[grunts]
-What? What?
-On your feet, boy.
Wait, wait, wait, wait.
Come on,
the king wants to see you.
Drunk!
What again?
Do you think this is fit?
Out, all of you, leave us.
-Do you think this is fit?
-I have been mistreated.
I... you...
you saw for yourself.
I demand that this...
this bear is punished.
Aethelwold, your years do not hide the
fact that you are a disappointment.
-May I ask why?
-That you need to ask
tells your father
all that he needs to know.
What?
That you are an unsuitable heir.
That is what.
Then I will change.
-You should.
-I will.
All I ask is that you
become a man and quickly.
Today... Today, I promise.
Am I excused?
[mutters indistinct]
I'm not convinced
he is my son.
If his mother was not
already dead
I would have her
beheaded for adultery.
[chuckles]
If I'm to fall
in the battles that will come,
he cannot be king.
-You favor Alfred?
-I do.
Even though
he is often weak in body?
Well, that his illness does
not tie him to his bed,
that shows the strength
of my brother.
Alfred is my heir, he knows it.
And when the time comes,
Odda, my friend, you must steer
the Witan to make this choice.
My Lord...
[thunder rumbles]
It's done.
Should be safe for now.
They say Danes
rarely come here.
What did Storri say to you, to
make you bind his mouth and...?
-He threw a curse.
-Saying what?
It's not important.
I responded with the branch.
-What are you doing?
-You know what I'm doing.
I'm removing the last
of his curse with a kiss.
I don't want to.
If you want to go to the Danes
then go find a new lord.
It's me they wish to kill.
-You sound like a child.
-I'm offering you a choice.
You're talking
through your arse.
I'm sitting on my arse.
So your arse
is cleverer than you,
-it can do two things at once.
-Thank you.
[thunder rumbles]
Your tongue is sharp, woman.
[laughing]
-Show me again.
-No...
You're right.
We can't go to young Ragnar.
But we should wait for him
to find us, which he will.
He will want to know the truth.
In the time between,
we stay alive.
We pass the time.
Doing what?
Mm.
[groans]
[laughing]
I have given her some beauty
but she is a tool,
no more no less.
She is exactly as I'd hoped.
We said ten?
We said eight.
She's worth ten.
-Thank you.
Lord, Men have been asking
of you... and your woman.
-Danes or Saxon?
-Take your pick.
Five or more.
Make her sing.
[indistinct chatter]
Brida, we should leave.
There are men looking for us.
-From Ubba?
-I don't know.
Saxons and Danes
are looking for us
we seem to be
collecting enemies as we go.
Get to the horses!
Go! Go! Go!
-Out the way! Out the way!
-Hey!
[screams]
[grunting]
[bleating]
[groans]
[yelling]
[grunting]
Brida,
the horses are just there.
Wait there is another.
We have to go. Come.
[yelling]
Brida, the door.
Wait...
Wait... now!
[panting]
You are right, we should leave.
Whoever it was that sent them,
Ubba or your uncle,
they won't rest,
they'll be others.
I can't go home without help.
Uhtred,
you should forget Bebbanburg.
No. No, I won't vanish.
Nothing changes.
Kjartan and my uncle
will pay for Ragnar's death,
and I will have those lands.
How? With who's help?
-You said yourself, we only have Ubba--
-The English.
If we're dead to the Danes,
we have no choice.
There is no England!
The Danes have England.
No, there is one place,
south of here: it's Wessex.
They'll take one look at you
and kill you as a Dane.
Where as Ubba will kill me
as an Englishman.
With King Aethelred we have
a chance of everything.
What do you say?
Come with me.
[indistinct chatter]
Why do they stare?
They think you're pretty.
Huh!
Or they've never seen a Dane
so close, but they will.
[crowd booing]
We have business with the king.
Aethelred.
[man] Go home!
[Uhtred] I say we have
business with the king.
Do you not understand English?
Is that what you're speaking,
arseling? You sound like a Dane.
Why do you dress as a warrior
when you're clearly a farmer?
Farmer am I? I'd wager this
farmer against you at anytime.
We are here to see the king,
peaceably.
Uhtred, what are you doing?
What is it farmer:
first blood, or to the death?
Uhtred!
I'll be splitting your skull
boy, so one follows the other.
[crowd shouting indistinct]
Uhtred?
Father Beocca.
[laughing]
-Oh, my goodness.
-You know this arseling, Father?
I do. Yes, I do.
Uhtred, you're...
you're fully grown.
And you're old!
[laughing]
I am.
Oh, you're a man.
[Leofric] He claims
business with the king.
Yes. Yes, that's true.
But not with the king,
it must be with Alfred.
-You vouch for him?
-I vouch for him.
Yes, I will vouch for him.
God has sent you, surely.
You're a man.
Father, this is Brida,
my greatest friend.
-A woman...
-Yes.
I am.
I have tits.
I see.
Have their horses
fed and watered.
And I will inform Alfred
that you're here with me, both.
We need their weapons, Father.
-Why not inform the king?
-The king is busy.
But you will like Alfred,
he is an impressive man.
Come.
[bell tolls]
Do you like it?
I do.
It's beautiful.
You could rest here,
it's so quiet.
[Alfred]
Peaceful.
The... the Romans,
they built this courtyard
for just that purpose,
tranquility.
You're Alfred?
I am.
My Lord.
You are Uhtred. I hear word
you are a considerable warrior.
[chuckles] Not been tested, Lord,
not yet, and I've been lucky.
Well, luck is good.
Or so my own warriors say.
Now I haven't quite worked out
the theology of luck:
can there be luck
if God disposes?
If your God is with you,
you're a lucky man.
Yes. You're right.
Simply put but you are right.
With me,
we shall talk inside, briefly.
I spend
much of my time in here.
Do you read, Uhtred?
I was schooled as a child
by Father Beocca,
but I was not a good student.
There's much to know
outside of letters.
Oh, I am certain there is,
but do not underestimate
the power of the written word.
When a man dies, if nothing is
written, he is soon forgotten.
For instance,
who is remembering Earl Ragnar?
You know of Ragnar?
Father Beocca has talked
much about you, Uhtred.
He believed you a prisoner,
a slave to Earl Ragnar.
-Is that the case?
-Ragnar was a father to me.
I loved him.
Yet, in Eoferwic, they are
saying that you killed him.
They lie.
Karjartan, Karjartan,
is that how you pronounce it?
Kjartan?
Kjartan...
...has benefited most
from Ragnar's death,
he has taken his place
and is Earl Kjartan now.
A great lord, with ships.
That's written down?
Whatever I discover about
my enemies is written down.
It is in Kjartan's interest
to kill you, is it not?
He would not want Ragnar's son
to hear a different tale.
He would not wish him
to hear the truth, no.
No... And the Chieftain Ubba...
Although he himself
has now traveled north,
he has sent men to Mercia,
asking of your whereabouts,
but not your welfare I surmise?
How do you come by all of this?
I have eyes and ears
in each of the kingdoms.
One day, it is my hope
that all kingdoms will become
one united under one God.
One king?
If all men can agree, yes.
All that remains of England,
is Wessex.
The birth of an England,
the idea...
of a single kingdom...
called England
has to begin here.
There is nowhere else.
But for how long
will Wessex remain?
The fate of Wessex will be determined
by Englishmen, all Englishmen.
Only by joining together and
saving Wessex can we have England.
Only by saving Wessex
can we have a...
...a Northumbria,
a Bebbanburg.
And if Wessex
can't be saved?
Then we are all no more.
[bell tolls]
Prayers.
[breathes heavily]
And a little discomfort...
I will summarize.
The Danes
are gathering a great army,
they have, in fact,
gathered an army.
They gather where?
They have moved up river
from Lundene to Readingum.
They are settling as we speak.
But you say Ubba is in the
north, so who leads them?
-The Earl Guthrum leads them.
-I know Guthrum.
We will need every advantage
and Father Beocca considers you,
Uhtred of Bebbanburg,
to be an advantage,
whereas I believe
you are here solely to hide,
to save yourself.
I look at you and I see a Dane.
I see Uhtred of Nowhere, who
cares for no one, but himself.
Now, I must go to prayers.
You will join me?
[chuckles]
-If my Lord will excuse me?
-[Brida] Us both.
Of course. I expected as much.
-Father Beocca!
-Lord...
-Take your guests for refreshments.
-I will my Lord.
They may remain in Winchester,
but I hold you responsible.
Yes, Lord.
You should have gone along and prayed
with him, it would have bonded you.
He believes we are Pagans.
What Alfred believes is that
the Danes have abandoned you.
Ubba has abandoned us
there are other lords.
Most, if not all, follow Ubba.
So believe me girl,
you have been abandoned!
Yeah, you know everything
about the Danes don't you?
This way,
I want to show you something.
The Charters of Bebbanburg.
-Yeah, the land books, yeah.
-You kept them safe.
I have shown
them to Alfred he...
...he knows that you are
the Ealdorman by right.
I will continue to keep them
safe, but Uhtred, you...
You must behave
like an Ealdorman.
The charters have no meaning,
Northumbria belongs
to the Danes.
[Beocca]
It does not belong to the Danes,
it has been stolen by them.
[Brida]
If you want wealth, you take it!
You can't ignore what's true.
If the Danes are at Readingum,
I will go to Readingum.
-What?
-For what purpose?
For knowledge.
We have knowledge and you should
stay away from Danes.
For new knowledge.
You know where they're settling
but you don't know why.
[Beocca] We know their number
and their position.
Not their intention.
Am I a prisoner?
Their intention is to attack.
When?
Spring. It's always spring.
I'll go to Readingum
Where is it?
-It's too dangerous.
-Not for me.
-I'm a godless stain remember!
-So why spy for Alfred?
Because he is
an Ealdorman of England.
[indistinct chatter]
[door opens]
[Beocca]
Lord.
Regarding the conversion
of the Pagans to Christianity?
Yes, Lord?
How do we decide what is proper?
To enlighten them
or to kill them?
Spreading God's word
is of course our mission,
but I fear that the Pagans,
the true Pagans,
must first witness,
then feel his power.
-Uhtred... will return?
-Yes, he will return.
Yes, but how will he return?
As who? As what?
-I know this boy--
-This boy is now a man.
-I know his soul.
-Father Beocca, he has no soul.
And you say yourself, the Pagans
need to feel the power of God.
It is written now, here.
You may leave me.
We shall see what
the days bring, my Lord.
If resting through the winter
was their intention,
they would have
remained in Lundene. Yes?
It's you who is Alfred's spy.
The next step is to kill
for him. Will you do that?
Answer me this... If we were to cross this
river and find Guthrum, what would happen?
He'd kill us both.
We owe them nothing!
Alfred needs to know
about the Danes,
and I need to win his trust!
You'd think he'd deliver you
Bebbanburg, what if you're wrong?
Alfred, you have called council,
for what reason?
Lord forgive me, it may well be
for no good reason,
but we have a Pagan in court
who claims to have knowledge
regarding the Dane army.
-A Pagan?
-Forgive me, Lord, he is Uhtred of Bebbanburg.
I vouch for his word.
Uhtred.
Lord...
I have been to Readingum.
I have watched the Danes.
Their intention
is not to settle.
If it were, they would have
remained in Lundene.
You are saying what,
that they intend to attack?
-I am Lord.
-[Odda] We already know this.
Come spring,
they'll be at our door.
They will be marching within
days, Lord, I am sure of it.
How can you possibly
be sure of it?
The ground is sodden all
around, it makes no sense.
They have made their sacrifices.
The ordinary warriors
have caught and killed birds,
jackdaws.
This is only done
in the days before battle.
And they are hungry.
Then perhaps they have
eaten these jackdaws.
They have many hundreds of men
and horses, and few supplies.
They'll first seize a town
rich with grain and livestock.
I don't know the country well,
but I have traveled,
I believe
Abbendum is such a place.
To defeat the Danes you must meet
them on the road to Abbendum.
It will be within days, Lord.
You went to Readingum alone?
-With Brida.
-Why alone?
Why not?
Because for most of your life
you have lived as a Dane.
You look like a Dane,
you can speak
the language of a Dane,
therefore, I surmise you can
set a trap like a Dane.
Agreed, my Lord,
he imagines we are jackdaws.
[Aethelred]
Where, on the road to Abbendum?
Where would you choose
to meet their army?
I would choose the place
called Asec's Hill, Lord.
You would choose
or Guthrum would choose?
I have seen it, the pass narrows,
you cannot be out-flanked.
For the Danes to fight uphill,
it will be difficult,
but they'll be confident,
they do not fear West Saxons.
Why? Why do they not fear us?
They believe you to be farmers,
nothing more.
So even with the sun
in their eyes,
which is possible, they will
climb the hill to fight,
and that can be
to our advantage.
[Odda]
To our advantage, he says!
You have been here for a matter of days
and already you claim to be of Wessex?
This is nonsense, this is all
far too convenient, my Lord.
My Lord, my sword was made by
a Saxon smith.
My sword is for Wessex.
Do not interrupt a noble
when he is speaking!
-[Aethelred] Odda.
-I believe this man,
and this bag of rags that
follows him, to be imposters.
No army marches
as winter approaches, never.
Young Odda,
enough from you now!
My Lord.
You...
You have spoken and given
this council much to discuss.
My Lord.
Alfred, he's here at your
invitation. What now?
Should the Danes march,
we must face them.
And I would rather be
at the top of a hill
than on the flat.
I say we march to Asec's Hill.
But... take him.
Take them both
and make them secure.
My Lord? What is this?
I have spoken the truth!
-I have spoken the truth! Father Beocca!
-My Lord, please.
-Beocca, help me! Beocca!
-Have faith!
[grunting]
[man speaks foreign language]
Halt!
[man] Left flank, hold!
Hold!
Archers ready!
On my command.
For God. For Wessex.
For England!
[men cheering]